Are
the Chinese trying to save
their housing market?
September is the season
for new "bazookas", and
this year will be no
exception.  China has just
announced a series of
potential programs
and ideas that the media
predictably
calls a massive
stimulus, another
housing bailout
that will finally
get the Chinese
economy back on
track, as
they finally
admit that
it
went very off course last year,
despite all the previous "
bazookas."  You would
think that this would have to
happen at least from time
to time.  They
are offering
mortgages potentially
for 40 years to
make payments cheaper
for borrowers,
but in reality this is a
bailout for the
banking sector
, and as we know, the
banking sector in
China is in dire need of a
bailout.  So
the question really
is: are
the Chinese responding to the needs of
households
by trying to get
them to buy more
property and take out
mortgages, or
not?  Are they saying, "
Let's use
this as a hidden
incentive to
get more
interest income from the banks,
at least in
the short
term, and thus
get them back on the
path to profitability,
because we
think they have a
huge pile of
bad loans on their balance sheets
."  So Steve, China, it's
almost September, and this is
almost an annual
ritual every September.
The Politburo gets
together, the Congress,
you know, all these
bigwigs from the CCP
get together.
They discuss all
these ideas and come up with
this "bazooka" plan
that's going to
save the housing
market.  I often think
it's just to
make the Western
media go crazy, because the
Western media
loves any
Chinese stimulus.
But here we
have another
historic
housing rescue on the threshold of
September.
And Jeff, you know, these
40-year mortgages, this whole
idea that this is supposedly
something wonderful, and I know
that someday this
will happen in the US on a
large scale, because
there's this idea that we
can just
reduce your payment.
Why not 100?  Let's
do 100-year
mortgages, Steve.
We will reduce these payments
to almost zero.
Yes, but they don't
go down that much
, and that's the whole
point.  It's
like, "Hey, you might
save $50 or
$100 a month," and
it's supposed to
make a huge difference in
your budget, your
purchasing
power, and your
ability to afford a
home.  The reality
is that you're
just locking
people up in a residential
prison.  The problem is
that, as you
said, it looks
very good for the banks
only at first glance
.  I mean, you
collect all this
interest.  But you know
what I think they're
not taking into account here is
the fact that the
housing market is declining.  And
if people start
taking out 40-year mortgages
, and the market
continues to
fall and their
financial situation
changes, what
happens?  Well, we already
know.  This
is called a
financial crisis, when
people just walk
away and send
the keys back to the bank.
And now the banks
will be left with all this
on their hands.  So, I know,
in China... it's always the same
hope: "
Hey, we're going to
turn the
housing market around."  "This will turn
our economy around and everything
will be fine."  But I
think, I think you're
right.  This is just
another bailout for
mortgage lenders
.  But, as before,
Jeff, I don't think it's going to
work.
OK.  Yes, I
mean there are reasons
for skepticism, of course,
because recent
history is a pretty
good guide.  I
mean, everything that the
Chinese
economy and
banking sector has done
since, you know, the "
big bazooka" in
September 2024, when
everyone went crazy over
it, everything except the
Chinese
bond market is worth
noting.  Everyone was
delighted, but now it
seems like it doesn't exist.  This is
not mentioned anywhere, and no
one talks about the
September "bazooka" of 2024
, because its effect
was what it is—
that is, zero.  Despite the
trillions of yuan that
were borrowed, it
really happened.    The
central government has
really gone crazy
issuing bonds
.  It simply had no
impact on either
the economy or the
banking system.
So, on the one hand,
Steve, can't you
understand their
perspective from the
Chinese government's side?    The
housing sector, the
real estate sector,
is a huge
problem.  Prices in
China are not collapsing,
but they are constantly
going lower and lower.
It's almost like a slow
slide down year after
year, house prices
falling a little more,
a little more, a little
more.  How to
stop this?  I
mean, if you're sitting in
Beijing and Xi Jinping
threatens you with a
purge or, you know,
corruption charges: "Hey, fix the
housing market or
you're going to be sued."  I
mean, what are you
going to do?  You'll
essentially reach into your
very limited
toolbox and
try to
pull out everything
you can.  So
the idea is
that if we
introduce a 40-year
mortgage, stretch
the payments out
long enough, it will
make it
cheap enough to attract
more buyers into the housing market
, and more
buyers means that
house prices can
stabilize.  And
if housing prices
start
to stabilize,
perhaps that will attract
other buyers to the market
.  I
mean, I don't like to
use the phrase "
last hope" because
China doesn't believe in
such things, but at
this point it
looks like that.  It's
like, "Hey, what else are we
supposed to do?"
Well, let's try to make
mortgage payments
as cheap as
possible,
and maybe, as they say,
"throw something at the wall"
and it will finally
stick.  I almost
never
advertise and turn down the
vast majority of
offers that
come to me, but I
was very happy
to work with the
sponsor of
today's video
— Monetary Metals.  And the reason is that
they
solve a big
problem that I have
been pointing out for a
long time.
Gold is a safe
haven, but apart from
sitting in a
vault, it
does nothing.  Monetary Metals
fixes this.  They
allow you
to earn real
income in physical
gold without losing
ownership.  This is
not a fund, this is not a
paper
obligation, this is your
gold working for
you.  More gold is credited to your account every month
.  It's simple,
transparent and fully
insured.  If you
believe in gold as a
long-term store of
value,
like I do, this changes everything.
Go to
monetary-metals.com/snyder.  This is
monetary-metals.com/snyder to
find out all the details.
We sincerely thank them for
sponsoring
today's video
, and now let's get back
to the topic.
Yes, because they
bailed out all the
mortgage lenders
and banks, and, well, it didn't do
anything, as we
expected.  I
mean, they just
postponed
the problem until later.
That is, there has not
been a single
large-scale collapse of the
banking system yet.    The
problem is that
now we need to
get people
to buy, because in the
Chinese economy,
in particular, as you know,
Jeff, there is too much
construction, and
the situation there is a little
different from
ours.  People
invest and to some
extent speculate in the
housing market, whereas here
people usually
invest in the
stock market.  So,
you know, there was a
main thesis: if the
housing market is growing,
then
China's economy is growing.  And
now many are
focused on AI.  And
AI, you know, drives the
US economy, it
drives the
Chinese economy.  And I think
people are starting
to realize the
reality: what happens
if AI development
slows down?  And so
they start
looking around and
realize that they have
nothing.  We
need to get the
housing market
to recover.  So,
if you bail out
the lenders, you bail out
the developers, and prices
still fall,
what choice do you have?  You
should try to
save the buyer.  And
going to a 40-year
mortgage—I
mean, what
choice do you have?  They can't
lower interest
rates because they're afraid of
destroying their currency,
so it's out of the question.
So the only thing you
can do is
tell people, "Hey,
how about
going into debt for 40
years? Doesn't that
sound like fun?"
Yes, that is, yes, they
cannot lower
interest rates any
further.  It's not
just about that, is it,
Steve?  This is the banking
sector.  The banking
sector said, "
Enough. You have to
stop lowering
interest rates
because it's just
destroying our
profitability. And
in fact, we
need as much profitability as possible
to deal with
all the loans that
we've made over the last
15 years that are now
becoming bad."
Well, you're right.  From a
Chinese
perspective, it's like a
chicken and
egg problem.  It's like, "Okay, the
housing market
was shaky before, it was
a little weak. It was
n't, you know, feeling
great, but
the economy seemed to be
holding up. We're
talking about the period up
until 2020, the late
2010s, when they really
started to move into a
managed recession,
slowly letting the
air out of the
housing bubble. So the
housing sector
started to
slow down, but
the rest of the economy
seemed to be holding up.
You know, retail
sales slowed down a little bit
,
fixed
asset investment was obviously
down, but
industrial
production was
relatively stable.
Fast forward a
few years,
now the
housing bubble is being deflated
even faster, and that's
definitely having an impact on the
real economy. We've
seen retail
sales this year,
they're just terrible.
Numbers that you
would never have expected,
let's say, in 2019. Back
in 2019, retail
sales had never, at the
beginning of 2019,
retail sales had never
were below 8%
per year. Now
they're at zero.
In fact, one
month, a few
months ago,
they were
negative. So
now they're
doing numbers
that we never thought we'd
see in
China. Suddenly the
Chinese government says,
"What do we do here?
How do we get
consumption to grow?
households
to spend when
they don't want to, you
know, they don't
spend when
house prices and their
main means of
wealth accumulation
keep falling?
Well, we have to get
people, if they're not
spending in the
real economy,
to buy houses,
maybe that will support
prices, and if they
support prices,
maybe they'll
start spending in the
real economy again."
And you're right, Steve, the
main risk here is that
the only thing that's
supporting the
Chinese economy right now is two
things. The first one, as you
mentioned, is artificial
intelligence, which is a
real factor.
Chinese exports have
just taken off. But
it's not  leads to
the large-scale,
you know,
wealth creation, income creation, or
jobs creation that
you expect or
want from something like that
. And the other thing
is the export boom
in general. The Chinese
are producing more
goods than they
actually need
or can
afford
to buy at home, and they
're sending it
mostly to Europe,
but the Europeans are now
saying, "Hey,
wait a minute. We don't
want your stuff either."
So you're like, "
Okay, exports are
saving us a little bit, we're surviving on
exports. But
we're starting to
get pushback on
that. With
artificial intelligence,
you know, it's not a
sure thing. The domestic
situation in the Chinese
economy is not very
good. So all
roads and all paths
lead to
bailing out
housing again, because
what the hell are
we supposed to do?
Well, I think that's a
perfectly valid
point, Jeff, there's
no other option because, you know
, we got ahead of the curve
on tariffs, and it didn't
create
jobs. And then we
thought, "Oh, we need to
get ahead of the
oil price spike and the
closing of the Strait of Hormuz,
" and well, that did
n't
create
jobs either. Oh, artificial
intelligence, okay. Well
, no, that didn't
create
jobs either. So you start
looking at everything that's
happened in
the last few years, and
you come to the same
conclusion: nothing is
creating
jobs. And if it is,
it's only in the very, very
short term. So,
again, you know, you
can't blame them for that
. What
other choice do they have?
They don't know how
to grow an economy,
as you like to say.
They don't know how
to create
jobs, and the housing market
is the only thing the
Chinese government
really understands.
You build more
houses, that creates
jobs, and
soon the economy
starts to grow.
The problem is that they
have to be sold to someone.
But the issue that they
seem to be
missing is not that
maybe a 40-
year mortgage
will attract  people for
whom that $100 a
month or a few
hundred dollars a month -- I think you mean a
month -- maybe that's going to be the
deciding
factor. But
the reality is that
we're seeing the same thing
all over the world, in
every major
economy. Everything is
slowing down. The
labor market is not
creating new
jobs.
Wage growth
is slowing down. And
soon, at some
point, the number of
hours worked is
going to start to fall. And these, these
Chinese workers
are smart. They
come to work and
they see that the number of
incoming orders
is starting to decrease
. They're not stupid. They
understand very well what
that's going to mean. But the
Chinese government, as
you said, well, if there's nothing else
to do, well
, give them a 40-
year mortgage.
That's a very valid
point, Steve.
The weakness of the Chinese
economy is not
just in the housing market and
real estate.
Part of it is, as you
said, Chinese
workers know what's
going on, just like
their
American counterparts.
You know, consumer
confidence  in the US at
zero because Americans
know that the risk of
losing their jobs is the
biggest threat.
The Chinese know the
same thing. They see what's
ahead of them
. They see that the
manufacturing machine is not
working as well
as it should.
They understand what's
happening—it's
a slowdown, the
economic circumstances
—maybe not in a
global sense, like when you
look at the macro data in detail,
but from their
perspective they
understand
the dangers and the
vulnerabilities. So,
of course, they're
cutting back because
it's just prudent.
I also want to
emphasize that it's
not just about the 40-year
mortgage. The Chinese
government has announced a
few other measures that are
a little bit more "heavy
artillery." The
China Securities Regulatory Commission
has said that it will support
developers raising funds through
the sale of stocks and
bonds. So there's
some
liquidity support for developers. We were
also reminded of
that
when China Vanke again
reported
huge losses.
If you don't
remember, China Vanke
is one of the
quasi-state
developers, one of the
largest in the world,
that hasn't gone
bankrupt yet. They're
teetering on the edge,
but the local government
is supporting them with
liquidity and
other resources.
But they just
reported
huge losses:
the equivalent of
$2.2 billion,
or almost 15 billion
yuan, which
shows once again that nothing has changed in
China's real estate sector over the
past few years
.
Again, despite the "
bazooka" of 2024—
early 2024,
I think, in May—
which was called a
historic
rescue of the housing
sector. So all of these
measures
have failed time and time again.
They haven't been able to
really
restart the
real estate sector or the
real economy.
The banking sector
continues to
contract severely.
You know, in July, the
total amount of
social
financing and
yuan loans
fell at a
record pace.
You've never
seen anything like this before. The annual
the change in the total
loan
book is
at an all-time low
and has been
slowing down rapidly
over the last few
years. So it's
not really looking
good. But as you
said, Steve, I
think
your point is very apt.
It's not just about
real estate.
Chinese consumers
are saying about the overall
macroeconomic
picture in China: we don't
want to spend
money. We have to
save as much as possible
because we don't know
where this is going.
And that's what
makes me
worried about the banks.
Of course, we know that
the banks in China are buying
bonds, and everyone
is smiling a little bit, but who is
actually buying the
bonds? I would
say that it's the
Chinese banks, and, you
know, foreign
investors are buying
them in droves because they see
what's going to happen next. So
the question is,
even if you
come out and say, "
Okay, you know what? We're going to
give people mortgages for
40 or 50 years, or whatever."
It
doesn't even matter. "Well,
we're going to give people mortgages for 40 or 50 years, or whatever."  subsidies."
Will banks
lend in
this situation? I do
n't think they want
to lend at all. So, as
you said, they don't
want interest rates to come down
because their margins are
already squeezed. They
already have all these loans
on their balance sheets. They
know that these loans
are going to be bad.
They don't have enough
new
quality loans at
high enough
interest rates. So they
have to buy
government bonds.
The question is,
will they lend at all
in these
conditions? From my
perspective, I just
don't see it. Yes, there will probably be
some who
will lend, but
they're unlikely to
say, "Hey,
loans for everyone." And
the next thing we're
going to see is a flood of
money flooding the
Chinese economy
and spreading to the
global economy. I just don't
see that
happening.
Yes, that's one of the
most
underrated, if not
overlooked, aspects of the
Chinese system
right now, is this big
rotation, the rotation of
balance sheets, that's
happening in what
is probably the
largest
banking sector
on the planet.
China's banking sector is getting out of
all the
risky assets,
of course, everything that has to do
with
lending, and
into
government bonds.
You know, Steve, we've
been laughing about
this for the last few
years. Think back to 2024
, when the People's
Bank of China said, "
Hey, don't buy these
government bonds."
"You're not going to
buy them." "We're
going to do
massive stimulus
." "There's going to be a huge
supply of government
bonds." "You're not
going to own
Chinese
government
bonds." And the
Chinese bankers
laughed and
said, "Give
us more
bonds." And what
happened? Chinese
interest rates
fell rapidly in
2024. They
stabilized somewhat in
2025, but then they
went down again in
late 2025 and
early 2026, and
never came back up.
significantly. We're talking
about ultra-low
interest rates
across China. So the
more Chinese
banks move into
ultra-low government
bonds because
they're safe and
liquid, the
more their yields are squeezed
. The more
they pull back
from risky
lending in
the economy, the more they
say, "We don't
care what the
yields are." "We don't
care about the
yield differential." So it
doesn't matter whether
you lower rates or
raise them. We're
still not going to
lend. So
China's banking sector, along with
bond yields, not only
tells us
what happened and how
China got to
this point, they
also tell us that there's no
credibility to it
. In fact, the
bond market's reaction this
morning when
these
measures were announced was something
like, "We
don't see anything
new." "It's all the
same." So the
bond market is saying that we
don't see anything different
in China, in terms of
real estate, in terms of the
property sector, or in terms of
government programs. There's nothing there.
is changing.
They don't see anything in
the macroeconomics
that suggests that
things are about
to change and
start to get better.
China is really in
a mess, and you don't expect that
to change
anytime soon
.
You know, for
Jeff and I, there's a fear
of an
AI bubble. I
mean, I don't...
let's say, even
if it doesn't burst, it
just
slows down a little bit.
It's been supporting
so many economies around the
world.
Look at China:
if they lose,
say, 10% of their exports to
AI, well, if they even
cut back a little bit on their
chip exports, what
happens if they
go down a little bit? What
happens to the rest of
their economy? They
need all this AI
to
keep them afloat,
but it's not working. So
we're
back to the
problem again: banks don't
want to lend
even at low
interest rates, and
consumers say, "
Look, we don't
want to borrow
even at  low
interest rates." So
the problem again is that
when we look at
the world, the question is
: what happens if for
whatever reason the
AI ​​bubble starts to
burst,
slows down or
something changes?
There is no
real
economic
foundation under any of these big economies to
support the whole world. And that
is the problem
that I am pointing out:
when one falls, the others
will soon follow, and
China is kind of raising the
white flag, saying,
"Okay, we are basically
giving up." "We don't
know what to do,
so let's try this."
Let's try something,
because we have to
do something, and that
is never a good sign. I
always say, the
more the government thinks it has to do
, the
worse the situation is.
So the bigger the
bazooka, the bigger the
problem is behind
it. And, of course, that is the
verdict of the
bond market. Again
, the most important
signal from there is the actions of
Chinese banks,
which are refusing
to lend and to do
risky transactions
on  the benefit of government
bonds that
yield almost no income.
There's nothing worse
than a "depressed
economy" like that to
understand the state of
depressed conditions.
So the question really is,
what do you
do? If
you're sitting in Beijing,
you have a list of
options, but all the
buttons have been
pushed at least
a few times in the
last few years, and nothing has
really worked
. So in
a lot of ways it makes
sense to just
try to
do something about the
housing market, because you never
know—maybe it'll
work as a bottom,
maybe the sentiment will
change somehow. I don't think that's
likely, but
if you don't try,
you're definitely not going to make
any real difference,
because nothing is
moving forward right now.
In fact, I think
the statement from Xi Jinping
and the government is also very
telling. They're
basically waiting in China for
China to
lead what they
call the fourth
industrial
revolution. In other
words, yes, we
know that the
real estate sector is in
disarray. We know that
development is dead,
as far as it goes.
in the real economy.
Consumption is not very
high, but you know,
manufacturing is the
old way of
doing things. We
are going to lead a
whole new
future. And by the way,
we have absolutely no
idea how to
do it, but we are
looking forward
to a whole new
future. So don't
worry too much about
the rest of the stuff. In many
ways, you know,
bailing out the housing
sector is not really going to
change
things in China. It's
just to
buy
as much time as possible
until they lead
this fourth
industrial revolution
. The problem is,
if you're not leading the
Fourth
Industrial
Revolution and you don't know
how to get there, and
one of the technologies that is
leading it—artificial
intelligence—is
in a situation where in
the short
term, it can
go either way.
It's a really bad
situation, so I
mean, you can
understand what the
Chinese government is thinking, but
you can also
see what investors are thinking
in
China's banking sector. It's like
we're not seeing
anything that -- the odds of
everything going
absolutely right
are getting
smaller and smaller every day.
And you know, Jeff, you're right about
the point --
buying time. Look
around. It's not just
China. I think every
government in the world, every
central bank
is asking, "How do we
buy time?"  "Because they
think that if they
have more time,
everything will somehow
work itself out
. We'll
cut rates a little bit here or
there. We'll do
a little stimulus or
add some bonus. We'll
throw that into
the economy, and everything
will change. And I think what
we're seeing is a
real fear among
policymakers. And again
, not just in China,
but around the world,
they're asking, 'What
if this trend
continues?'"  "We're out of
ammunition. We've
done everything we can.
We've given people
money. We've subsidized
interest rates. We've, you know,
fixed the
banking system,
injected liquidity. We've
taken on so much
debt... we've done
everything, but nothing's
working. And I think what
we're seeing in China,
Jeff, from my
perspective, is a payback for them
. And if they
go down, the rest of the world won't be far
behind.
From October 9th to the 12th, I'm going to bring together a
group of about 40
serious investors
and financiers, along
with special
guests like Hugh
Hendry, Michael Green,
George Gammon, Brent
Johnson, and others, for four
days of discussing the
issues that really
matter. What's
next? Where are the
biggest risks
misjudged?
Where are the opportunities? What
needs to change our
thinking? And how do we
build a position
on that? This is not
a conference of
speeches. This is a
small group for
discussions, debates,
and practical advice.
So if you're running a  If you have
significant capital
or are seriously
interested in these
questions and want
to find answers in an
intimate circle,
apply
below.